<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
    <title>Mikel Ors - Software Development, Agile &amp; Culture</title>
    <subtitle>Mikel Ors&#x27; personal blog about Agile, Software Engineer best practices and something else</subtitle>
    <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://mikelors.com/atom.xml"/>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://mikelors.com"/>
    <generator uri="https://www.getzola.org/">Zola</generator>
    <updated>2025-01-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://mikelors.com/atom.xml</id>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Estaré en la Previa de la Bilbostack&#x27;25</title>
        <published>2025-01-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-01-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Mikel Ors
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://mikelors.com/posts/bilbostack25presentingtopic/"/>
        <id>https://mikelors.com/posts/bilbostack25presentingtopic/</id>
        
        <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;mikelors.com&#x2F;posts&#x2F;bilbostack25presentingtopic&#x2F;previaBilbostack.png&quot; alt=&quot;Previa Bilbostack&quot; title=&quot;Previa Bilbostack&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Este es el abstract de la charla que daré en la &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;bilbostack.com&#x2F;laprevia&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Previa de la BilboStack&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; 
el próximo 24 de enero rodeado de grandes profesionales:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;la-trampa-del-trabajo-duro-en-el-desarrollo-de-software&quot;&gt;La trampa del trabajo duro en el desarrollo de software&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trabajar muy duro siempre se ha considerado como algo positivo. Entendiéndolo como el hecho de &lt;strong&gt;esforzarse al 
máximo&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;, asegurar que siempre estamos &lt;strong&gt;permanentemente ocupados&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; haciendo cosas e incluso yendo más allá de lo 
necesario metiendo las &lt;strong&gt;horas extra&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; que haga falta. ¿Quién no querría un equipo formado por personas que trabajan 
así? Pues si lo que queremos hacer es Software de calidad y que aporte valor, tal vez trabajar así no sea la mejor idea.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Creo en la Ingeniería de Software como un trabajo intelectual y creativo que se realiza en colaboración 
con personas, en un entorno en constante cambio. En esta charla, &lt;strong&gt;exploraremos el principio de &amp;quot;Work Smarter, 
Not Harder&amp;quot; aplicado al desarrollo de software&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. Explicaré por qué creo que el trabajo duro puede afectar 
negativamente no sólo a los desarrolladores, sino también a la calidad del software que producen. También 
compartiré ideas y estrategias que nos han funcionado a mí y a mis equipos, siempre con el objetivo de generar 
software de calidad que aporte valor.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(click on Read More to see the English version)&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</summary>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>How I created a self-managed blog, secure and maintainable</title>
        <published>2024-04-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2024-04-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Mikel Ors
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://mikelors.com/posts/howicreatedthisblog/"/>
        <id>https://mikelors.com/posts/howicreatedthisblog/</id>
        
        <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;So, I finally made the decision to create my own personal website. Alright, I&#x27;ve purchased the domain 
mikelors.com, but what comes next?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-i-wanted&quot;&gt;What I wanted&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had some clear priorities for my webpage. Mainly three&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;👷 &lt;strong&gt;Minimal maintenance&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: I&#x27;m aiming for a setup without the need for plugins or frequent updates. I have
past experiences with CMSs like Joomla, Wordpress, Drupal... and they are cool, but require maintenance effort that I 
don&#x27;t want. &lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;🔐 &lt;strong&gt;Secure with no effort&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: I don&#x27;t want a website that could be hacked easily and, at the same time, I don&#x27;t 
want to spend time and effort on security features. &lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;🤌 &lt;strong&gt;Self-managed&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: I don&#x27;t want a SaaS platform like Wordpress.com, Blogger, Whatever where the owner could change
their policies, change their prizes or simply ban me for any reason. &lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this article is to demonstrate how I achieved this setup. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Long story short is asking a good friend that already had a personal website that I guessed that could have 
similar priorities than me. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</summary>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Book review - Accelerate by Nibole Forsgren, Jez Humble and Gene Kim</title>
        <published>2023-08-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2023-08-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Mikel Ors
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://mikelors.com/posts/bookreviewaccelerate/"/>
        <id>https://mikelors.com/posts/bookreviewaccelerate/</id>
        
        <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Lean methodologies, DevOps, small cycles, CI&#x2F;CD, no overtime, freedom, quality, culture, sustainable work… cool stuff.
A lot of people talk about them in positive terms but Nicole Forsgrem, Jez Humble and Gene Kim decided to go one 
step further: &lt;strong&gt;demonstrate that these things work&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</summary>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Book review - The Black book of the Programmer by Rafael Gómez Blanes</title>
        <published>2023-08-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2023-08-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Mikel Ors
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://mikelors.com/posts/bookreviewblackbookoftheprogrammer/"/>
        <id>https://mikelors.com/posts/bookreviewblackbookoftheprogrammer/</id>
        
        <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rafael Gómez Blanes&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; wrote this amazing book that I think is a must for all developers and managers in the IT world. 
His experiece in the Software Development world is the key he uses to highlight what works and what does not. 
It’s a &lt;strong&gt;book that touches&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; almost all or perhaps &lt;strong&gt;all the parts of Software Development Culture&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; the way I see it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, if there is a book where trying to highlight just a few quotes is difficult, this is the book. I think it 
is also the book that I have recommended the most to friends and colleagues.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</summary>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Book review - Engineering management for the rest of us by Sarah Drasner</title>
        <published>2023-08-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2023-08-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Mikel Ors
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://mikelors.com/posts/bookreviewengineeringmanagementfortherestofus/"/>
        <id>https://mikelors.com/posts/bookreviewengineeringmanagementfortherestofus/</id>
        
        <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sarah Drasner&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; wrote this marvelous book about technical team manager role.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a fact that most of us started leading by accident. We studied to be the best technicians and, &lt;strong&gt;suddenly, 
one day we find ourselves leading a team&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. And no one probably has ever told us about people, communication and 
so many other things necessary to do it well. If this is your case, read Sarah’s book. If it is not, if you are 
not a manager, even if you never want to be a manager… read it anyway. We should all know what a good manager does.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</summary>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Book review - Remote + It doesn&#x27;t have to be crazy at work by Jason Fried and David H. Hansson</title>
        <published>2023-08-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2023-08-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Mikel Ors
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://mikelors.com/posts/bookreviewremote/"/>
        <id>https://mikelors.com/posts/bookreviewremote/</id>
        
        <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Ok, I’ve cheated here: &lt;strong&gt;it’s not one book but two&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. But written by the same guys, following a similar philosophy 
and they are very easy to read with big typeface and lots of great art. Actually they have some other cool books.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jason Fried and David H. Hansson&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; work at 37signals, a software company where the culture is very important and 
special. They are &lt;strong&gt;pioneers working remotely&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; and they encourage their people to work smart, in a calm environment, 
at a &lt;strong&gt;sustainable pace&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;, promoting respect for their lifes from work. They go against growth as a measure of a 
company’s success.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really love these 2 books.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</summary>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Book review - Slack by Tom DeMarco</title>
        <published>2023-08-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2023-08-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Mikel Ors
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://mikelors.com/posts/bookreviewslack/"/>
        <id>https://mikelors.com/posts/bookreviewslack/</id>
        
        <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Organizations are effective only to the extent that all their workers are totally and eternally busy. Written by 
&lt;strong&gt;Tom DeMarco&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; more than 20 years ago, this book fights again this idea. &lt;strong&gt;Companies need workers&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; with &amp;quot;slack&amp;quot;, &lt;strong&gt;with 
gaps of freedom&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; in their they by day. These gaps will allow your company to change, improve, reinvent and grow.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</summary>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Property based testing — A practical approach in Python with Hypothesis and Pandas</title>
        <published>2022-06-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2022-06-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Mikel Ors
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://mikelors.com/posts/propertybasedtesting/"/>
        <id>https://mikelors.com/posts/propertybasedtesting/</id>
        
        <summary type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-property-based-tests-are&quot;&gt;What Property based tests are&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Property based tests are a type of tests that &lt;strong&gt;check properties of our functions that should always be true&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. 
They allow us to define a group of inputs following some rules and check that property on them in a single test.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</summary>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Clean Code — A practical approach</title>
        <published>2022-04-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2022-04-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Mikel Ors
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://mikelors.com/posts/cleancodeapracticalapproach/"/>
        <id>https://mikelors.com/posts/cleancodeapracticalapproach/</id>
        
        <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;After giving some talks about Clean Code I have decided to summarize the most important things in an article. Because 
there is a lot of posts and information in the net about Clean Code, I think that a new article talking about it simply 
explaining some the principles is not going to be very worthy.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this article I will try to give you a practical approach to Clean Code. I will not go deep into the theory, &lt;strong&gt;I want 
to show how I write Clean Code&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</summary>
        
    </entry>
</feed>
